Inventory of the L. Wolfe Gilbert papers, 1907-1971
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
L. Wolfe Gilbert papers
1907-1971
Gilbert, L. Wolfe (Louis Wolfe), 1886-1970
04374
21.5 cubic ft. (35 boxes) + 1 oversized box
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Contains the papers of L. Wolfe Gilbert, a Russian-born American songwriter known for his work as part of the Tin Pan Alley group.
Biography of L. Wolfe Gilbert
L. Wolfe Gilbert (1886-1970) was an American lyricist and composer during the twentieth century. Known as the "Dean of Tin Pan Alley", Gilbert was born in Odessa, Ukraine and immigrated to the United States with his family as an infant. He later moved to New York City and started working in vaudeville as a teenager. Gilbert wrote his first hit song, "Waitin' for the Robert E. Lee" in 1912 and went on to write more than 250 songs, including "Down Yonder" (1921), "Lucky Lindy" (1927), and "Peanut Vendor' (1931). His songs were performed and recorded by numerous performing artists, including Fred Waring, Count Basie, and Xavier Cugat. Gilbert also wrote lyrics and composed for radio, motion pictures, and television, and his work included writing music for the "Eddie Cantor Show", writing the lyrics for the song "Ramona" (which became the first ever motion picture theme song for the movie "Ramona" in 1936), and writing the lyrics for "Hopalong Cassidy March" (which became the theme song for Hopalong Cassidy's movies and television show during the 1940s and 1950s). In addition to his musical activities, Gilbert was an active member of the American Society of Composers, Authors, and Publishers, serving as its director from 1941 to 1944. He was also the author of his autobiography Without Rhyme or Reason (1956).
Scope and Content
Collection contains L. Wolfe Gilbert's correspondence (business and personal), song lyric notes (handwritten, typed, and mimeographed), and subject files (containing clippings, sheet music, and printed materials). Collection also contains photographs (mostly of Gilbert and other show business personalities), original manuscripts of Gilbert's autobiography Without Rhyme or Reason, and several scrapbooks (which contain clippings, correspondence, and song lyrics). Numerous 78 rpm phonograph records of L. Wolfe Gilbert songs recorded by various artists (including Fred Waring, Count Basie, and Xavier Cugat), published sheet music of Gilbert's songs, award plaques and certificates, and a handful of original musical scores are also present in the collection.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
The Theodore Dreiser papers at the University of Pennsylvania contain correspondence with Gilbert, The Lilac Domino [collection]: Operetta in Three Acts at the University of Wisconsin contains works by Gilbert, and an oral history with Gilbert resides at Columbia University.
Acquisition Information
This material was received from Rose Wolfe Gilbert (spouse) from 1972 to 1991 and the UNC Charlotte, J. Murrey Atkins Library in 2018.
Access Terms
American Society of Composers, Authors, and Publishers.; Composers -- United States -- 20th century.; Lyricists -- United States -- 20th century.; Lyric writing (Popular music); Popular music -- Writing and composing -- United States.; Popular music -- United States -- 20th century.; Phonograph records.; Scrapbooks.
Arts, Humanities, and Social Sciences; Music; Performing Arts
Container List
- Series I. Career
  - Sub-series 1. General
    - ASCAP Membership Meeting reports, 1952-1955 (Box 5)
    - ASCAP printed materials, 1939-1969 (Box 6)
    - ASCAP West Coast Membership Meeting reports, 1950-1952 (Box 5)
    - ASCAP West Coast Membership Meeting reports, 1955-1957 (Box 6)
    - ASCAP, 1925-1971 (Box 2)
    - ASCAP, 1930-1968 (Box 5)
    - Plaque - "To Wolfie with much affection and gratitude for devoted service from the West Coast 'Guys and Gals' of ASCAP,", 1961 (Box 31)
    - Plaque - To a Great American for the Millions of Happy Hours You Have Given Countless People from The Larry Finley Show, KFWB, 1953 July 24 (Box 31)
    - Plaque - To L. Wolfie Gilbert on his Seventieth Birthday, the Members of the Board of Directors of the American Society of Composers, Authors and Publishers salute him:…, 1956 August 31 (Box 31)
    - Plaque of appreciation from West Coast Membership of ASCAP, 1959 February 25 (Box 31)
    - Radio scripts - Art and Dotty Todd, 1954 April 23 (Box 10)
    - Radio scripts - Ed Lowry Show, undated (Box 10)
    - Radio scripts - Eddie Cantor, 1933-1934, undated (Box 9)
    - Radio scripts - Eddie Cantor, 1932-1934, undated (Box 10)
    - Radio scripts - Jack Benny, 1952 February 3 (Box 9)
    - Without Rhyme or Reason manuscripts, undated (Box 12)
    - Without Rhyme or Reason manuscripts, undated (Box 13)
    - Without Rhyme or Reason manuscripts, undated (Box 14)
  - Sub-series 2. Lyric notes
    - A Garden in Encino, 1940 (Box 17)
    - A Life Time, Is No Time, undated (Box 18)
    - A Mender of Broken Hearts, undated (Box 18)
    - A Waltz in the Clouds, undated (Box 19)
    - A Weepin' and a Wailin' Song, undated (Box 17)
    - Are You Going to the Texas Oil Man's Ball?, undated (Box 17)
    - As Love Goes Marching On, undated (Box 17)
    - At Journey's End, undated (Box 17)
    - At the Double Diamond Ranch, undated (Box 17)
    - Baby, You Slay Me, undated (Box 17)
    - The Bells of Montebello, undated (Box 17)
    - Benny the Bow-Legged Bowler, undated (Box 17)
    - Bless Your Little Heart My Dear, undated (Box 17)
    - Bo Weevil, undated (Box 17)
    - Bouncin' on the Bayou, undated (Box 17)
    - Broken Dolly and Me, undated (Box 17)
    - Broken Dreams to Mend, undated (Box 17)
    - Calling All Cars, undated (Box 17)
    - Child Wonder, undated (Box 17)
    - Chiquita, 1926, 1928 (Box 17)
    - Colorado Sunset, undated (Box 17)
    - The Cosmopolitan, undated (Box 17)
    - Cotton Moon, undated (Box 17)
    - The Cross Roads of the World, undated (Box 17)
    - Cry Baby, undated (Box 17)
    - Cry of a Soul, undated (Box 17)
    - The Cry of the Wolf, undated (Box 17)
    - Cuttin' Corners, undated (Box 17)
    - Dancing with an Angel, undated (Box 17)
    - The Dartmouth Twirl, undated (Box 17)
    - Don't Let Me Down, undated (Box 17)
    - Down Yonder, 1951-1952 (Box 17)
    - Entre Nous, undated (Box 17)
    - Ess Ess Mein Kindt (notes, score, and 45 RPM vinyl record), 1966 (Box 17)
    - Eternally Yours, undated (Box 17)
    - Forever and a Day, 1929 (Box 17)
    - Funny Paper Capers in a Dream, undated (Box 17)
    - Gimme a Girl, undated (Box 17)
    - The Greatest Enemy of Love, undated (Box 17)
    - Hotcha Yascha Lovanoff, 1938 (Box 17)
    - I Can't Say Manyanna, undated (Box 17)
    - I Could Be Wrong, undated (Box 17)
    - I Laughed at Love, undated (Box 17)
    - I Live for You, undated (Box 17)
    - I Lost My Way, undated (Box 17)
    - I Miss My Swiss, 1925 (Box 17)
    - I Smiled at the Moon, undated (Box 17)
    - If I Were You and You Were Me, undated (Box 17)
    - I'm Buying a Bond for My Baby, 1942-1944 (Box 17)
    - I'm the Best Bad Gal in Town, undated (Box 17)
    - I'm Winding Up My Affairs, undated (Box 17)
    - In a Wistful Vista, undated (Box 17)
    - In My Corral, undated (Box 17)
    - In My Network Nightmare Dream, undated (Box 17)
    - In the Cradle of Your Arms, undated (Box 17)
    - Is That Asking too Much?, undated (Box 17)
    - It's Always a Waltz, undated (Box 17)
    - Junior Auxiliary, 1950-1961 (Box 18)
    - The Kiss that was Stolen, undated (Box 18)
    - Labels, undated (Box 18)
    - Laffs and Lies, 1959 (Box 18)
    - The Land I Love, undated (Box 18)
    - Land of Glamorous Girls, 1939 July 27 (Box 18)
    - Last Night I Missed You in My Dreams, undated (Box 18)
    - The Last Time I Saw Paris (recitation), undated (Box 18)
    - Let Doctor Cantor Worry for You, undated (Box 18)
    - Lips Like the Rose, undated (Box 18)
    - Listening, undated (Box 18)
    - Little Bronze Lady in the Harbor, 1940 (Box 18)
    - London's Truckin' Now, undated (Box 18)
    - Lost a Man's Best Pal, undated (Box 18)
    - Love Called Me This Morning, undated (Box 18)
    - Lucky Lindy, 1927-1971 (Box 18)
    - Mama Don't Want No Peas an' Rice an' Cocoanut Oil, 1952 (Box 18)
    - Man Behind the Badge, 1955 (Box 18)
    - Maria, My Own, undated (Box 18)
    - The Masquers, 1960 (Box 18)
    - Meet the Family, undated (Box 18)
    - The Meeting at the Summit, undated (Box 18)
    - Mio Rio de Janeiro, 1936 (Box 18)
    - Miscellaneous, 1926-1942, undated (Box 19)
    - Mister Publisher, undated (Box 18)
    - Music, Wine, an Old Bouquet, undated (Box 18)
    - My Absent Lover, undated (Box 18)
    - My Diary, undated (Box 18)
    - My Midnight Cinderella, undated (Box 18)
    - My Mother's Eyes, undated (Box 18)
    - My Pillow, undated (Box 18)
    - My Smoke Dream Lady, 1936 (Box 18)
    - My Son, My Son, 1939 (Box 18)
    - Neath California Skies, undated (Box 18)
    - Neath the Moon at Saskatoon, 1937 (Box 18)
    - Nobody's Lost on the Wholesome Trail, undated (Box 18)
    - Octogenarian, undated (Box 18)
    - The Old Arm Chair, undated (Box 18)
    - On Christmas Day, undated (Box 18)
    - One More Smile, undated (Box 18)
    - One of a Kind, undated (Box 18)
    - Only the Brave, undated (Box 18)
    - Over Yonder Hills, undated (Box 18)
    - Peanut Vendor, undated (Box 18)
    - Ramona, 1955-1970 (Box 18)
    - Rather do Without You Baby, undated (Box 18)
    - Ringing the New Year In, undated (Box 18)
    - Shades of Night, undated (Box 19)
    - She's a Gypsy from Brooklyn, undated (Box 19)
    - Song of Mojave, undated (Box 19)
    - The Song of the Rabbit, undated (Box 19)
    - Songwriting scrapbook, 1925, undated (Box 25)
    - The Sweetest Day, undated (Box 19)
    - Take Good Care of My Baby, undated (Box 19)
    - Take It with a Grain of Salt, undated (Box 19)
    - There Goes My Sugar Girl, undated (Box 19)
    - There's No Song Like an Old Song, undated (Box 19)
    - There's No Substitute for Love, undated (Box 19)
    - There's Nobody Else But You, 1942 (Box 19)
    - The Things That Count, undated (Box 19)
    - The Things We Love Will Live Again, undated (Box 19)
    - This Belongs to You, undated (Box 19)
    - Three Blind Mice, undated (Box 19)
    - Three Little Sugar Girls are We, undated (Box 19)
    - Tournament of Roses, 1952-1961 (Box 18)
    - Two Against One - 'Taint Fair, 1938 (Box 19)
    - Two Hearts in Silhouette, undated (Box 19)
    - Waiting for the Robert E. Lee, 1929-1968 (Box 19)
    - We Went to Work in the Morning, undated (Box 17)
    - We're Gonna Hit - Hit - Hitler, undated (Box 19)
    - When a Latin Falls in Love, undated (Box 19)
    - Who Do You Belong to?, undated (Box 19)
    - Why am I the Way, I am About You, undated (Box 19)
    - You're Only Fooling Yourself, undated (Box 19)
  - Sub-series 3. Articles
    - Anesthesia Hit Parade, Best Hypo to a Songwriter, 1963 January 9 (Box 22)
    - Does Practical Payola Pay Off?, 1960 November (Box 22)
    - Down in Melody Row, 1925-1926 (Box 22)
    - Hits That Almost Missed, 1960 January 6 (Box 22)
    - I Tangled with Sime, undated (Box 22)
    - The Illiteracy Test, 1965 (Box 22)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1926-1959 (Box 22)
    - The Original Giveaway Program, 1956 November 19 (Box 22)
    - The Penny Arcade, 1961 November 14 (Box 22)
    - Rubbed Elbows with -, 1961 January 8 (Box 22)
    - The Song Belters, 1963 November (Box 22)
    - They're Playing Our Song, undated (Box 22)
    - Truly a Yankee Doodle Dandy, undated (Box 22)
    - What Have You Written Lately?, 1961 January 4 (Box 22)
    - Who Wrote That Song?, undated (Box 22)
    - With His Hat in His Hand, 1956 January 4 (Box 22)
- Series II. Audiovisual materials
  - ASCAP group photograph, Coliseum, Treasure Island (3), 1940 September 24 (Box 34)
  - Phonograph record album, 1948-1949, undated (Box 36)
  - Phonograph record albums (2), 1926-1942, undated (Box 27)
  - Phonograph record albums (4), 1912-1957, undated (Box 25)
  - Phonograph record albums (5), 1937-1955, undated (Box 26)
  - Phonograph record albums (6), circa 1915-1955, undated (Box 29)
  - Phonograph record albums (6), circa 1912-1936, undated (Box 30)
  - Phonograph record albums (6), 1923-1966, undated (Box 28)
  - Phonograph records - ASCAP on Parade (8), undated (Box 34)
  - Phonograph records - assorted (3), 1951-1955 (Box 32)
  - Phonograph records - Cavalcade of Music Concert (8), 1940 September 24 (Box 33)
  - Phonograph records - Greek Relief Fund Show (6), 1941 February 25 (Box 32)
  - Phonograph records - Let's Write a Song (2), 1940 June 7 (Box 34)
  - Phonograph records - Men of Music - Shakespeare (2), undated (Box 33)
  - Phonograph records - Ridin' the Range (2), undated (Box 34)
  - Photographs (some signed), 1929-1953, undated (Box 34)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 9)
  - Photographs, 1936-1968, undated (Box 11)
  - Reel-to-reel tape recordings of Gilbert's work (2), undated (Box 26)
- Series III. Printed materials
  - The ASCAP Biographical Dictionary of Composers, Authors, & Publishers, edited by Daniel I. McNamara (contains Gilbert), 1952 (Box 3)
  - The ASCAP Biographical Dictionary of Composers, Authors, & Publishers, edited by Daniel I. McNamara (contains Gilbert), 1948 (Box 4)
  - The ASCAP Biographical Dictionary of Composers, Authors, & Publishers, Second Edition, edited by Daniel I. McNamara (contains Gilbert), 1952 (Box 3)
  - American Society of Composers, Authors, and Publishers Biographical Dictionary, compiled and edited by The Lynn Farnol Group, Inc. (contains Gilbert), 1966 (Box 3)
  - Binder - sheet music in English & Chinese, 1929, undated (Box 21)
  - Birthday - 65th, 1951 August (Box 22)
  - Birthday - 70th, 1956-1957 (Box 22)
  - Birthday - 71st, 1957-1968 (Box 22)
  - Birthday - 72nd, 1958 August (Box 22)
  - Birthday - 73rd, 1959 (Box 22)
  - Birthday - 74th, 1960 August (Box 22)
  - Birthday - 75th, 1961 (Box 22)
  - Birthday - 76th, 1962-1963 (Box 22)
  - Birthday - 77th, 1963 (Box 22)
  - Birthday - 78th, undated (Box 22)
  - Birthday - 79th, undated (Box 22)
  - Birthday - 80th, 1966 (Box 22)
  - Birthday - 81st, 1967 (Box 22)
  - Birthday - 82nd, 1968 (Box 22)
  - Cole Porter, 1956 (Box 22)
  - Deep in My Heart by Elliott Arnold (inscribed by author), 1949 (Box 1)
  - Eddie Cantor, 1950 April 3 (Box 22)
  - Elson's Pocket Music Dictionary, 1909 (Box 23)
  - Examiner Christmas Benefit Show, 1954 December 17 (Box 23)
  - Ferde Grofe, 1967 April 3 (Box 22)
  - Friars' Club, 1949-1964 (Box 23)
  - Galley proofs of The Zionist Record Annual on Gilbert, 1952 September (Box 35)
  - George Jessel, 1946, undated (Box 22)
  - The Guardian, 1962-1971 (Box 22)
  - Gus Edwards, 1955, undated (Box 22)
  - Harmony and Harmonics by Arthur Lange, Mus. D. (inscribed by author's wife), 1958 (Box 1)
  - A History of Popular Music in America by Sigmund Spaeth (inscribed by author), 1948 (Box 4)
  - The Hollywood Reporter, 1965 November 16 (Box 23)
  - I Ring Doorbells by Russell Birdwell (inscribed by author), 1939 (Box 4)
  - I'll Cry Tomorrow by Lillian Roth (inscribed by author), 1954 (Box 4)
  - Irving Berlin, 1936 January 20 (Box 22)
  - Jimmy McHugh, 1954 (Box 22)
  - Jules Bledsoe, 1941 May 15 (Box 22)
  - The Mirth of a Nation by Jimmy Lyons (inscribed by author), 1953-1954 (Box 3)
  - Legal material, 1949-1969 (Box 23)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, 1921-1969 (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous programs, 1925-1969 (Box 23)
  - More Poems by Nick Kenny (inscribed by author), 1948-1951 (Box 1)
  - Music books, 1915-1949, undated (Box 15)
  - Music books, 1915-1943 (Box 16)
  - Music charts, 1951-1961 (Box 23)
  - News clippings scrapbook, 1936-1937 (Box 35)
  - News clippings scrapbook, circa 1917-1924 (Box 27)
  - News clippings scrapbook, circa 1930-1938 (Box 27)
  - News clippings scrapbook, circa 1937-1942 (Box 36)
  - Palace Theater, 1923 (Box 23)
  - Passport to Paris by Vernon Duke (inscribed by author), 1955 (Box 3)
  - Paul Whiteman, 1913-1928 (Box 22)
  - The Politician by Stephen and Ethel Longstreet (inscribed by author), 1959 (Box 4)
  - Press book, 1907-1922 (Box 35)
  - Publicity for Without Rhyme or Reason, 1955-1958 (Box 14)
  - Sheet music - A, 1917-1961 (Box 19)
  - Sheet music - B, 1931-1952 (Box 19)
  - Sheet music - C, 1914-1961 (Box 19)
  - Sheet music - D, 1920-1955 (Box 20)
  - Sheet music - E, 1966, undated (Box 20)
  - Sheet music - F, 1929-1954, undated (Box 20)
  - Sheet music - G, 1919-1952 (Box 20)
  - Sheet music - H, 1912-1951 (Box 20)
  - Sheet music - I, 1914-1955 (Box 20)
  - Sheet music - J, 1928 (Box 20)
  - Sheet music - L, 1917-1966 (Box 20)
  - Sheet music - M, 1911-1956 (Box 20)
  - Sheet music - miscellaneous, 1936-1953 (Box 21)
  - Sheet music - N, 1927-1954 (Box 21)
  - Sheet music - O, 1915-1962 (Box 21)
  - Sheet music - P, 1915-1958 (Box 21)
  - Sheet music - R, 1927-1953 (Box 21)
  - Sheet music - S, 1916-1950 (Box 21)
  - Sheet music - T, 1912-1952 (Box 21)
  - Sheet music - U, undated (Box 21)
  - Sheet music - W, 1926-1954 (Box 21)
  - Sheet music - XYZ, 1913-1958 (Box 21)
  - Sing-along sheets, 1927-1954 (Box 19)
  - They All Had Glamour by Edward B. Marks (inscribed by author), 1944 (Box 1)
  - Travel, 1955-1957 (Box 23)
  - Variety, 1940-1969 (Box 35)
  - Vaudeville by Joe Laurie, Jr. (inscribed by author), 1958 (Box 1)
  - W.C. Handy, 1954 (Box 22)
  - William Boyd - Hopalong Cassidy, 1950-1965 (Box 22)
  - Without Rhyme or Reason by L. Wolfe Gilbert, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Young Americans, 1969 (Box 23)
- Series IV. Personal items
  - Certificates (4), 1959-1968 (Box 34)
  - Certificates (4), 1960-1968 (Box 27)
  - Certificates, 1938-1967 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1938-1951 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1952-1969, undated (Box 8)
  - Gilbert family material, 1920-1970 (Box 6)
  - Plaque - Appreciation from the Conference of Jewish Women's Organizations, Los Angeles, 1963 May 23 (Box 31)